in the medical arena in cancer research is the fact that the refrigerator was invented. (Laughter) And so -- yeah, I know. We're not doing so well here. I don't want to miniaturize the progress and everything that's been done in cancer research. Look, there is like 50-plus years of good cancer research that discovered major, major things that taught us about cancer. But all that said, we have a lot of heavy lifting to still do ahead of us. Again, I will argue that the primary reason why this is the case, why we have not done that remarkably well, is really we're fighting blindly here. And this is where medical imaging comes in. This is where my own work comes in. And so to give you a sense of the best medical imaging that's offered today to brain cancer patients, or actually generally to all cancer patients, take a look at this PET scan right here. Let's see. There we go. So this is a PET/CT scan, and what you'll see in this PET/CT scan is the CT scan will show you where the bones are, and the PET scan will show you where tumors are. Now, what you can see here is essentially a sugar molecule that was added a small little tag that is signaling to us outside of the body, "Hey, I'm here." And those sugar molecules are injected into these patients by the billions, and they're going all over the body looking for cells that are hungry for sugar. You'll see that the heart, for example, lights up there.
dans la recherche médicale contre le cancer est l'invention du réfrigérateur. (Rires) Ouais, je sais. On ne s'en sort pas bien. Je ne veux pas minimiser le progrès et tout ce qui a été fait comme recherches sur le cancer. Plus de cinquante années de bonne recherche sur le cancer ont permis de découvrir des choses majeures sur le cancer. Cela dit, il y a encore énormément de travail à accomplir. Je peux soutenir que la raison principale de notre échec est que nous nous battons à l'aveuglette. C'est là que l'imagerie médicale entre en jeu, que mon travail entre en jeu. Pour vous donner une idée de la meilleure imagerie médicale qui est offerte aux patients de cancer du cerveau et à tous les patients de cancer, regardez ce TEP. Voilà. Ceci est un TEP/TDM et ce que vous y voyez est que le TDM vous montrera où sont les os et le TEP vous montrera où sont les tumeurs. Ce que vous pouvez voir ici est en gros une molécule de sucre qui a été ajoutée, une balise qui, nous dit, à nous à l'extérieur du corps : « Je suis là. » Ces molécules de sucre sont injectées par milliards dans le patient et elles parcourent le corps à la recherche de cellules voulant du sucre. Vous voyez par exemple que le cœur s'éclaire ici
That's because the heart needs a lot of sugar. You'll also see that the bladder lights up there. That's because the bladder is the thing that's clearing the sugar away from our body. And then you'll see a few other hot spots, and these are in fact the tumors. Now, this is a really a wonderful technology. For the first time it allowed us to look into someone's body without picking up each and every one of the cells and putting them under the microscope, but in a noninvasive way allowing us to look into someone's body and ask, "Hey, has the cancer metastasized? Where is it?" And the PET scans here are showing you very clearly where are these hot spots, where is the tumor. So as miraculous as this might seem, unfortunately, well, it's not that great. You see, those small little hot spots there. Can anyone guess how many cancer cells are in any one of these tumors? So it's about 100 million cancer cells, and let me make sure that this number sunk in. In each and every one of these small little blips that you're seeing on the image, there needs to be at least 100 million cancer cells in order for it to be detected. Now, if that seemed to you like a very large number, it is a very large number. This is in fact an incredibly large number, because what we really need in order to pick up something early enough to do something about it, to do something meaningful about it, well, we need to pick up tumors that are a thousand cells in size, and ideally just a handful of cells in size. So we're clearly pretty far away from this. So we're going to play a little experiment here. I'm going to ask each of you to now play and imagine that you are brain surgeons.
car le cœur a besoin de beaucoup de sucre. La vessie aussi s'éclaire car la vessie est ce qui élimine le sucre de notre corps. Quand vous voyez d'autres points, ce sont des tumeurs. C'est une technologie extraordinaire. Pour la première fois, elle nous permet de voir l'intérieur du corps sans avoir à prélever chacune des cellules pour les observer au microscope, de façon non invasive, elle permet de regarder l'intérieur du corps et voir si le cancer a métastasé, et où. Les TEP ici montrent clairement où sont les tumeurs. Aussi miraculeux que cela paraisse, malheureusement, ce n'est pas si génial. Vous voyez ces petits points ici. Selon vous, de combien de cellules cancéreuses sont composées les tumeurs ? Environ 100 millions de cellules cancéreuses. Je vais m'assurer que vous perceviez bien cela. Chacun de ces points que vous voyez sur l'image doit être composé d'au moins 100 millions de cellules cancéreuses afin d'être détecté. Si cela vous semble être un nombre important, c'est le cas. C'est un nombre incroyablement grand car nous avons besoin, afin de détecter quelque chose assez tôt pour pouvoir agir, faire quelque chose de significatif, nous devons détecter les tumeurs qui font un millier de cellules et, idéalement, seulement quelques cellules. Nous en sommes clairement loin. Nous allons faire une petite expérience. Je vais vous demander à tous de jouer et d'imaginer que vous êtes neurochirurgien.
And you guys are now at an operating room, and there's a patient in front of you, and your task is to make sure that the tumor is out. So you're looking down at the patient, the skin and the skull have already been removed, so you're looking at the brain. And all you know about this patient is that there's a tumor about the size of a golf ball or so in the right frontal lobe of this person's brain. And that's more or less it. So you're looking down, and unfortunately everything looks the same, because brain cancer tissue and healthy brain tissue really just look the same. And so you're going in with your thumb, and you start to press a little bit on the brain, because tumors tend to be a little harder, stiffer, and so you go in and go a little bit like this and say, "It seems like the tumor is right there." Then you take out your knife and start cutting the tumor piece by piece by piece. And as you're taking the tumor out, then you're getting to a stage where you think, "Alright, I'm done. I took out everything." And at this stage, if that's -- so far everything sounded, like, pretty crazy -- you're now about to face the most challenging decision of your life here. Because now you need to decide, should I stop here and let this patient go, risking that there might be some leftover cancer cells behind that I just couldn't see, or should I take away some extra margins, typically about an inch or so around the tumor just to be sure that I removed everything? So this is not a simple decision to make, and unfortunately this is the decision that brain cancer surgeons have to take every single day as they're seeing their patients. And so I remember talking to a few friends of mine in the lab, and we say, "Boy, there's got to be a better way." But not just like you tell a friend that there's got to be a better way. There's just got to be a better way here. This is just incredible. And so we looked back. Remember those PET scans I told you about, the sugar and so on. We said, hey, how about instead of using sugar molecules, let's maybe take tiny, tiny little particles made of gold, and let's program them with some interesting chemistry around them. Let's program them to look for cancer cells. And then we will inject these gold particles into these patients by the billions again, and we'll have them go all over the body, and just like secret agents, if you will, go and walk by every single cell in our body and knock on the door of that cell, and ask, "Are you a cancer cell or are you a healthy cell? If you're a healthy cell, we're moving on. If you're a cancer cell, we're sticking in and shining out and telling us, "Hey, look at me, I'm here."
Vous êtes dans la salle d'opération, il y a un patient devant vous et votre tâche est de vous assurer que la tumeur est enlevée. Vous regardez le patient, la peau et le crâne ont déjà été enlevés, vous regardez le cerveau. Tout ce que vous savez de ce patient est qu'il a une tumeur de la taille d'une balle de golf dans le lobe frontal droit de son cerveau. C'est à peu près tout. Vous regardez et, malheureusement, tout se ressemble car le tissu cérébral cancéreux et le tissu cérébral sain ont exactement le même aspect. Vous utilisez votre pouce, vous appuyez un peu sur le cerveau car les tumeurs sont un peu plus dures, rigides et donc vous y allez, vous faites un peu comme cela, la tumeur semble être juste ici. Puis vous sortez votre scalpel et retirez la tumeur, morceau par morceau. En extrayant la tumeur, arrive un point où vous pensez : « J'ai fini, j'ai tout extrait. » A ce point-là, si -- jusqu'ici tout semblait assez fou - vous allez devoir prendre la décision la plus difficile de votre vie. Car vous devez décider si vous devriez vous arrêter, laisser le patient partir, risquer qu'il reste des cellules cancéreuses que vous n'avez pas vues, ou vous prenez une marge supplémentaire, en général 3 cm autour de la tumeur, pour vous assurer d'avoir tout enlevé. Ce n'est pas un choix facile et, malheureusement, c'est la décision que les neurochirurgiens doivent faire chaque jour avec leurs patients. Je me souviens avoir parlé à des amis au labo et avoir dit : « Il doit y avoir une meilleure façon de faire. » Pas comme vous dites à un ami qu'il doit y avoir une meilleure solution. Il devait y avoir une meilleure solution. C'est simplement incroyable. On est reparti du début. Souvenez-vous de ces TEP dont je vous ai parlé, avec le sucre. Au lieu d'utiliser des molécules de sucre, nous avons pensé utiliser de petites particules d'or en les programmant chimiquement. Les programmer pour chercher les cellules cancéreuses. Ensuite, nous injecterons ces particules d'or par milliards chez les patients, elles parcourront le corps et, comme des agents secrets, iront voir chaque cellule de notre corps, frapperont à la porte, et demanderont si elle est cancéreuse ou saine. Si elle est saine, on continue. Si elle est cancéreuse, la particule reste, brille et nous dit : « Regardez-moi, je suis là. »
And they'll do it through some interesting cameras that we developed in the lab. And once we see that, maybe we can guide brain cancer surgeons towards taking only the tumor and leaving the healthy brain alone. And so we've tested that, and boy, this works well. So I'm going to show you an example now. What you're looking at here is an image of a mouse's brain, and we've implanted into this mouse's brain a small little tumor.
On pourrait les voir grâce à des caméras inventées au labo. Si vous voyons cela, nous pouvons guider les neurochirurgiens pour qu'ils enlèvent la tumeur sans toucher au cerveau sain. Nous avons testé cela, cela fonctionne bien. Je vais vous montrer un exemple. Vous voyez ici une image du cerveau d'une souris. Nous avons implanté une tumeur dans le cerveau de cette souris.
And so this tumor is now growing in this mouse's brain, and then we've taken a doctor and asked the doctor to please operate on the mouse as if that was a patient, and take out piece by piece out of the tumor. And while he's doing that, we're going to take images to see where the gold particles are. And so we're going to first start by injecting these gold particles into this mouse, and we're going to see right here at the very left there that image at the bottom is the image that shows where the gold particles are. The nice thing is that these gold particles actually made it all the way to the tumor, and then they shine out and tell us, "Hey, we're here. Here's the tumor."
Cette tumeur grossit, nous avons demandé à un docteur d'opérer la souris comme si c'était un patient et d'enlever la tumeur, morceau par morceau. Alors qu'il fait cela, nous prenons des photos pour voir où sont les particules d'or. Pour commencer, nous injectons les particules d'or dans la souris, ce que nous allons voir ici tout à gauche, l'image en bas, c'est l'image qui montre où sont les particules d'or. Ce qui est bien, c'est que les particules d'or sont arrivées dans la tumeur, elles brillent et nous disent : « Nous sommes là. La tumeur est là. »
So now we can see the tumor, but we're not showing this to the doctor yet. We're asking the doctor, now please start cutting away the tumor, and you'll see here the doctor just took the first quadrant of the tumor and you see that first quadrant is now missing. The doctor then took the second quadrant, the third, and now it appears to be everything. And so at this stage, the doctor came back to us and said, "Alright, I'm done. What do you want me to do? Should I keep things as they are or do you want me to take some extra margins around?" And then we said, "Well, hang on." We told the doctor, "You've missed those two spots, so rather than taking huge margins around, only take out those tiny little areas. Take them out, and then let's take a look." And so the doctor took them away, and lo and behold, the cancer is now completely gone. Now, the important thing is that it's not just that the cancer is completely gone from this person's brain, or from this mouse's brain. The most important thing is that we did not have to take huge amounts of healthy brain in the process. And so now we can actually imagine a world where doctors and surgeons, as they take away a tumor, they actually know what to take out, and they no longer have to guess with their thumb. Now, here's why it's extremely important to take those tiny little leftover tumors. Those leftover tumors, even if it's just a handful of cells, they will grow to recur the tumor, for the tumor to come back. In fact, the reason why 80 to 90 percent of those brain cancer surgeries ultimately fail is because of those small little extra margins that were left positive, those small little leftover tumors that were left there. So this is clearly very nice, but what I really want to share with you is where I think we're heading from here. And so in my lab at Stanford, my students and I are asking, what should we be working on now? And I think where medical imaging is heading to is the ability to look into the human body and actually see each and every one of these cells separately.
Nous pouvons voir la tumeur mais nous ne la montrons pas encore au docteur. Nous demandons au docteur d'enlever la tumeur, vous verrez qu'il n'a enlevé que le premier quart de la tumeur qui a maintenant disparu. Le docteur a ensuite enlevé le deuxième, le troisième et il semble qu'il ait tout enlevé. A ce point-là, le docteur nous dit : « J'ai fini. Que voulez-vous que je fasse ? Devrais-je laisser cela ainsi ou devrais-je prendre une marge supplémentaire ? » On lui a dit d'attendre. On lui a dit : « Vous avez oublié ces deux endroits, plutôt que de prendre des marges autour, enlevez seulement ces petites zones. Enlevez-les puis on regardera à nouveau. » Le docteur les a enlevées et voilà, le cancer a complètement disparu. Ce qui est important n'est pas juste que le cancer ait complètement disparu du cerveau de cette personne ou de cette souris. Le plus important est que nous n'avons pas eu à enlever trop de cerveau sain au cours du processus. Nous pouvons imaginer un monde où les docteurs et chirurgiens, en enlevant les tumeurs, savent quoi enlever et n'ont plus besoin d'utiliser leur pouce. Voici pourquoi il est très important d'enlever ces restes de tumeur. Ces restes de tumeur, même si ce ne sont que quelques cellules, vont grossir et reformer la tumeur, la tumeur va revenir. La raison pour laquelle 80% à 90% des chirurgies du cerveau finissent par échouer est à cause de ces petites marges supplémentaires laissées, ces petits restes de tumeurs laissés derrière. Cela est très bien, mais ce que je veux partager avec vous est ma vision de la direction prise. Dans mon labo à Stanford, mes étudiants et moi nous demandons ce sur quoi nous devrions travailler. Je pense que l'imagerie médicale se dirige vers la capacité à regarder l'intérieur du corps humain et à voir toutes ces cellules séparément.
The ability like this would allow us to actually pick up tumors way, way earlier in the process, way before it's 100 million cells inside, so we can actually do something about it. An ability to see each and every one of the cells might also allow us to ask insightful questions. So in the lab, we are now getting to a point where we can actually start asking these cancer cells real questions, like, for example, are you responding to the treatment we are giving you or not? So if you're not responding, we'll know to stop the treatment right away, days into the treatment, not three months. And so also for patients like Ehud that are going through these nasty, nasty chemotherapy drugs, for them not to suffer through those horrendous side effects of the drugs when the drugs are in fact not even helping them.
Cette capacité nous permettrait de détecter des tumeurs bien, bien plus tôt, avant d'avoir 100 millions de cellules, afin de pouvoir agir. La capacité de voir toutes ces cellules nous permettrait de poser des questions pointues. Au labo, nous arrivons au point où nous pouvons poser de vraies questions aux cellules cancéreuses, par exemple, savoir si elles répondent au traitement qui leur est donné. Si elles ne répondent pas, nous pourrons l'arrêter immédiatement, après quelques jours et non trois mois. Pour des patients comme Ehud qui prennent des médicaments de chimiothérapie très mauvais, pour qu'ils ne souffrent pas de ces épouvantables effets secondaires des médicaments alors que ces médicaments ne les aident même pas.
So to be frank here, we're pretty far away from winning the war against cancer, just to be realistic. But at least I am hopeful that we should be able to fight this war with better medical imaging techniques in the way that is not blind. Thank you. (Applause)
Pour être franc, nous sommes encore loin de gagner la guerre contre le cancer, je suis juste réaliste. Mais au moins j'ai espoir que nous devrions pouvoir nous battre avec de meilleures techniques d'imagerie afin de ne pas le faire à l'aveuglette. Merci. (Applaudissements)